<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A right comfortable treatise containing fourteene pointes of consolation for them that labor and are laden: VVritten by D. Martin Luther to Prince Friderik Duke of Saxonie, he being sore sicke, thereby to comfort him in the time of his great distresse. Englished by W. Gace.</title>
            <title>Tessaradecas consolatoria pro laborantibus et oneratis. English</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106344</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842062</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6686</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06516)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6686)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 640:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A right comfortable treatise containing fourteene pointes of consolation for them that labor and are laden: VVritten by D. Martin Luther to Prince Friderik Duke of Saxonie, he being sore sicke, thereby to comfort him in the time of his great distresse. Englished by W. Gace.</title>
                  <title>Tessaradecas consolatoria pro laborantibus et oneratis. English</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
                  <author>Gace, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Vautrollier dwelling in the Blacke Friers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1578.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by William Gace, of: Luther, Martin. Tessaradecas consolatoria pro laborantibus et oneratis.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Consolations for them that labor and are laden.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Suffering --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6686:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6686:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RIGHT COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORTABLE TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISE CONTAINING fourteene pointes of conſolation for them that labor and are laden: <hi>VVRITTEN BY D. MARTIN Luther to Prince Friderik Duke of Saxonie, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſore ſicke, thereby to comfort him in the time of his great diſtreſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Engliſhed by W. GACE.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Vautrollier dwelling in the Blacke Friers. 1578.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:6686:2"/>
            <head>Martin Luther.</head>
            <p>I Did write this booke in the beginning of my procedings, to the moſt gracious Prince Fride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rik Duke of Saxony, when he was ſore ſicke. Now many thought good that it ſhould be imprinted, but when it had bene eftſones imprinted, it was ſo corrupted and made vnperfect, that I found many wordes wanting, which I my ſelfe could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture what they were: howbeit the ſentences I haue reſtored after a ſort, and ſuch as I thinke I had in the beginning. Neither haue I thought it good now to chaunge or adorne them as I could: For I will in this booke ſhewe a teſtimonie of my proceeding, and gratifie the aduerſaries, that they may haue wherewith to exerciſe their malice. It is ſufficient for me if I pleaſe my Lord Chriſt &amp; his Sainctes: I reioyce from my hart, and giue thankes to my God that I am enuied and hated of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and his Impes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6686:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL M. HENRIE DALE CITIZEN AND <hi>MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of the citie of London, VV. Gace wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth grace and peace from God the Father through Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Anifold are the miſeries of mans life, wherewith he is greatly grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and ſundry wayes moleſted, inſomuch as Iob ſayth that man that is borne of a woman hathe but a ſhort time to liue, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with miſerie. For he beginneth his life with teares &amp; weeping, he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it with ſorrow &amp; trouble, and endeth it with dolour and payne. Wherefore it is no maruell if ſome haue thought that it is the beſt thinge not to be borne, and the next to dye quickly: and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome haue mourned and wept at the birthes of their friendes, and ſolemnly reioyced at their burialls. For what could they being deſtitute of the light of God and true religion, ſee in this life but trouble &amp; miſerie? Yea the godly themſelues, as they haue in all ages ſuffered many afflictions in this life, ſo haue they paſſed through the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:6686:3"/>as through a ſtraunge countrie. For if heauen be our countrie, what is the earth els but a place of baniſhment? wherein being exiled from true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes and pleaſures, we liue in a ſtate vnquiet, troubleſom, and many wayes miſerable, as to him that ſhall duely conſider the ſundry troubles that are incident to all ſortes of men in this life, wil ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily appeare.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch then as this life is ſo miſerable, as both the Saincts of God haue pronounced of it, the very heathen haue accounted it, &amp; daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience proueth it, &amp; yet neuertheleſſe we, ſeeing God hath placed vs in it, muſt remaine therein till he call vs away: great neede we haue of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation &amp; encouragement as may be a meane to make vs paſſe the time thereof without grudging &amp; impatiencie. For of our ſelues we are very fraile &amp; weake, not able to reſiſt, much leſſe of power to ouercome, as is manifeſt by them, who in the time of affliction haue through impacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie murmured againſt God, albeit there both haue bene, and are many, who being not of them ſelues but by other meanes ſupported, haue patiently ſuſtained many troubles and miſeries.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I truſt that my labor ſhall not be thought ill beſtowed, but rather profitably em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied, which I haue taken in tranſlating this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe into the Engliſhe tongue, for that it tendeth chiefly to the conſolation of ſuch as are in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſtreſſe. For that which the title of this booke portendeth, the matter thereof ſufficiently proueth, namely that it containeth conſolations for them that labor and are laden, that is, that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:6686:3"/>afflictions and troubles in this life: ſo that they which ſhall diligently read and peruſe the ſame, may be ſo confirmed thereby, that when they be troubled with hardnes of aduerſitie, they may not be ouercome or throwne downe therewith: when they be moleſted with griefe &amp; ſorrow, they may be alſo delited with ſpirituall ioy: when they be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen diſtreſſed with troubles and afflictions, they may receiue courage againe, being cheared with ſundry conſolations, &amp; ſo patiently ſuffer accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods will whatſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe him to lay vpon them.</p>
            <p>Howe great this commoditie is, it plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth not onely by this, that the feelinge of the preſent affliction is thereby aſſwaged, but by this alſo, that it is a meane to moue and make vs to obey Gods will, which otherwiſe we woulde be readye to reſiſt, and to ſuffer patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereas otherwiſe we woulde by impatien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie be ſtubborne agaynſte the righteouſnes of God.</p>
            <p>Wherefore foraſmuche as I am not ignoraunt that the croſſe is vſually incident to the godly, and that through many afflictions we muſt enter into the kingdome of God, I am bolde to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende this treatiſe to all the godly in generall, to be read of them to their ſingular commoditie and comfort, but eſpecially to your worſhippe, whoſe godly conuerſation both of a longe tyme hath bene, and dayly is an euident teſtimonie of your ſyncere and vnfeyned profeſſion of Chriſte his religion: deſiringe you to eſteeme thereof, not accordinge to the quantitye or
<pb facs="tcp:6686:4"/>outward appearance (for then ſhall you make but ſmall account of it, being both litle in quantitie, &amp; adorned with no eloquent tearmes or glorious wordes) but according to the frute that the godly ſhall reape by diligent reading therof. For pearles and precious ſtones for the moſt part are in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie but ſmall, and in outward appearance ſimple, which in value notwithſtanding are great and in vertue excellent. Howbeit being ſufficiently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of your well accepting hereof, I will not ſtand vpon this point, leſt I ſhoulde ſeeme in any wiſe to dout of it, but doe deſire Almighty God, that as you haue hitherto liued in his feare, ſo ye may dayly increaſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly continue in the ſame euen vnto the ende.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your vvorships at commaundement <hi>W. GACE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6686:4"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST FAMOVS PRINCE AND LORD, THE LORD FRIDERIK, Duke of Saxonie, &amp;c, his very good Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Lorde and Sauiour Ieſus hathe left a commaundement which pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth indifferently to all Chriſtians, that we ſhould performe the duties of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, or rather (as the Scripture calleth them) the workes of mercy to the afflicted and miſerable: that we ſhould viſit the ſicke, endeuour to deliuer the captiues, and doe ſuch like to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, whereby the preſent euills may be ſomewhat aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaged. Hereof our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath in him ſelfe ſet forth vnto vs a moſt manifest &amp; ſingular example, wheras of his exceeding loue toward mankind, he came downe from the boſom of the father into our miſeries and into our priſon, that is, into our fleſh and moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable life, and tooke the puniſhment of our ſinnes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him ſelfe, that we might be ſaued: according as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai ſayth chap. <hi>43:</hi> Thou haſt laden me with thy ſinnes, and wearied me with thy vngodlines, &amp;c. If there be any whom this ſo manifeſt &amp; ſingular an example doth not ſtirre vp, and the authoritie of Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:6686:5"/>added therunto doth not moue to performe theſe workes of charitie, ſurely he ſhall worthely in the last iudgement heare the voice of the angrie Iudge: Goe thou curſed into euerlaſting fire. For I was ſicke and thou didſt not viſit me, but being altogether vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the exceeding benefits which I bestowed on thee and all the world, thou didſt not euen in the most ſclender duties relieue or helpe thy brethren, no not me Chriſt in my brethren.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch therefore moſt famous Prince, as I ſee your Grace to be ſore ſicke, and that Chriſt alſo is ſicke in you, I haue thought it my dutie to viſit your Grace by writing ſomewhat vnto you. For I can not diſſemble, that I doe not heare the voice of Chriſt our of your Graces body and fleſhe crying to me, and ſaying: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am ſicke here. For theſe euills, namely ſicknes and ſuch like, not we Chriſtians onely, but Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alſo our Lord and Sauiour, in whom we liue, doth ſuffer, as he manifestly witneſſeth in the Goſpell: VVhatſoeuer ye doe to the leaſt of mine, ye doe it vnto me. Nowe although we owe this duetie to all that are ſicke in generall, that we doe viſit and comfort them, yet doe we owe it chieſly to them that be of the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold of ſaith. For Paule doth plainely diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene aliens, and them that profeſſe the ſame faith with vs, or with whome we haue ſome alliance. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. <hi>6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit I haue other reaſons alſo of my duetie. For I know that I as one of your Graces ſubiectes, togither with the reſt of your ſubiectes ought to be moued with your Graces ſicknes, and to be as it were ſicke togither with you, as the member with the head, in whom all our good eſtate, ſafetie, and proſperitie conſiſteth. For we
<pb facs="tcp:6686:5"/>acknowledge your Grace to be as a certain Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by whom God at this day giueth health to Germanie, as in time paſt by him he gaue health to Syria. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euen the whole Romane Empire hath your Graece in admiration, doth reuerence and honour you as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the countrie, as a ſingular ornament and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the whole Empire, but eſpecially of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nation.</p>
            <p>Neither do we owe this only to your Grace, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you as much as we are able, and as it were to beare the preſent caſe with you, but much rather to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for your health and recouerie: which I hope is done with all diligence and endeuour of your Graces ſubiectes. As for my ſelfe, whom many notable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and pleaſures haue made a dettour to your Grace more then the reſt, I acknowledge that I ought by ſome ſingular duetie to declare my thankfulnes. But becauſe in this ſclendernes of abilitie and power, I am able to performe no notable thinge, D. George Spalatine, who is your Graces Chaplen, aduertized me that I ſhoulde doe well to make ſome ſpirituall conſolation &amp; ſend it to your Grace, for that that would be a thing very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto you. VVherefore I thought it not good to doe contrary to the aduertizement of my frende, and therefore haue I gathered togither theſe fourteene chapters, being compriſed as it were in a table, and haue intitled them
<note n="*" place="margin">That is, fourteen, or that which conſiſteth of that number.</note> Teſſaradecas, that they might be in ſteede of fourteene Sainctes which our ſuperſtition made and called the driuers away of all euills. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit this is not a ſiluer but a ſpirituall table, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, not the walls of temples are to be adorned, but the godly mind is to be comforted and confirmed. And I hope that it will be very profitable to your Grace in
<pb facs="tcp:6686:6"/>this preſent ſtate. Nowe it is diuided into two partes, whereof the former contayneth ſeuen conſiderations of euills, whereby the preſent griefes and troubles are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated and aſſwaged. The latter containeth likewiſe ſeuen conſiderations of good thinges tending to the ſame ende. VVherefore I deſire your Grace to take this my ſimple labour in good parte, which I pray God ye may ſo enioy, that by diligent reading and conſideration of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ye may haue ſome eaſe. I humbly commend me to your Grace.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble and obedient ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect MARTIN LVTHER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:6686:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle Paul in the 15. chapter of his Epiſtle to the Romanes ſpeaking of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian comfort, ſayth: Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, VVhatſoeuer things haue ben written afore time, were written for our learning, that we through pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and comfort of the Scriptures might haue hope. VVhereby he plainly teacheth that our comforts muſt be taken out of the holy Scriptures. Nowe the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vſe two ſortes of comfort, inaſmuch as they commend vnto vs the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of two ſortes of things, namely of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill things and of good things, according as the wiſe man ſayth: In the day of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction remember proſperitie: &amp; in the day of proſperitie be mindful of affliction. For the holy Ghoſt knoweth that euery thing is of ſuch ſort &amp; ſo great to man, of what ſort and how great his opinion is thereof. For that which is counted vile &amp; nothing eſteemed, doth litle moue, either with loue if it come, or with griefe if it depart. VVherefore he laboureth moſt earneſtly
<pb facs="tcp:6686:7"/>to call man from the opinion &amp; affection of thinges, which vvhen he hath brought to paſſe, all thinges are then indifferent. Novve foraſmuch as this calling is done eſpecially by the vvorde, vvhereby the opinion is transferred from the thinge, vvhich is preſently felt to the thing vvhich either is abſent or not preſently felt, it is by good reaſon that vve shall haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort but by the Scripture, which in the day of affliction calleth vs to the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of proſperitie, vvhich is either preſent or to come: alſo in the day of proſperitie calleth vs to conſider affliction. But that theſe conſiderations may be more eaſie vnto vs, vve vvill diuide either of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeuen partes. To the former shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the euills vvhich are to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a man: Firſt vvithin him ſelfe: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly before him: Thirdly behind him: Fourthly beneath him: Fiftly on the left hande: Sixtly on the right hand: Seuenthly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue him.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6686:7"/>
               <head>THE FIRST CHAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER OF THE FIRST CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, which is of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward euil.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is certaine and moſte true, whether man beleeue it or not, that there can be none ſo great trouble &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation in man, which is the worſt of the euills which are in him, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moe and greater euils are there in him then which he feeleth. For if he felt his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, he ſhould feele euen hell: for he hath hel in him ſelf. Dooſt thou demaund, how?
<note place="margin">Man hath hell in him ſelfe, which is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt euill in him.</note> The Prophet ſayth: All men are lyars. And againe: Euery man liuing is altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vanitie. Now to be a lyar and vaine is to be voyd of veritie, &amp; not to be in deed: but to be without veritie, and not to be in deede, is to be without God, and to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: and this is to be in hell, and to be condemned. Therefore God mercifully chaſtening vs, openeth vnto vs and layeth vpon vs the ſmaller &amp; lighter euils, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that if he ſhould bring man to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his euill, he ſhould forthwith pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6686:8"/>in a moment: howbeit he hath giuen it to ſome to haue a feeling and taſte of it, of whome it is ſayd: He bringeth downe to the graue, and fetcheth vp againe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſay rightly who cal corporal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings certaine aduertizements of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward euill. And the Apoſtle Heb. 12 cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fatherly chaſtenings of God, ſaying:
<note place="margin">VVhy God ſcourgeth euery ſonne whom he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiueth.</note> He ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he receiueth. Which he therefore doth, that by theſe ſcourges and ſmall euills he may expell thoſe great euills, leaſt we ſhould at any time feele them, as it is ſayd Prouerb. 22: Fooliſhnes is bound in the hart of the child, and the rod of correction ſhall driue it away. Are not godly parents alſo more grieued by their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they be theeues or euill, then if they be wounded? yea they doe them ſelues beat and wound them that they may not be euill.</p>
               <p>What therefore is the cauſe that this very euil is not felt?
<note place="margin">Godſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to feele his greateſt euill, and why.</note> truely as I haue ſaid, God diſpoſing it it commeth ſo to paſſe, that man may not be vtterly diſcouraged, if he ſhould ſee his moſt inward euils. For God hideth them, and will haue them ſeene by only faith, while he ſheweth them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6686:8"/>by the euill that is felt. Therefore in the day of affliction or when thou ſuffereſt euil thinges, remember good thinges: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der howe great a good thinge it is not to know all the euill, be mindfull of this good thinge, and the euil which thou feeleſt ſhal leſſe diſquiet or trouble thee. So againe in the day when thou enioyeſt good thinges, remember euill things, that is, while thou art not grieued with thoſe that be very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills in deede, in this want of griefe be thankefull, and remember the very euills, then will it come to paſſe that thou ſhalt leſſe feele the euill that is felt.</p>
               <p>It is manifeſt therefore that the want of griefe is alwayes greater in man in this life, then griefe, not for that the whole euill is not preſent, but becauſe there is no opinion or affection thereof by the goodnes of God, who hideth it. Hereupon we ſee them to whom it is giuen to behold their very euill, howe rigorous and cruell they are againſt them ſelues, howe they count it nothing whatſoeuer they can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in their whole life, ſo as they feele not their hel. So would euery one doe, if he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther felt or firmely beleeued his inward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euill:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6686:9"/>he would of his owne accord call for outward euills, he would ſport in them, &amp; would neuer be more ſad or ſorrowfull, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when he had no euills, as we know ſome of the Sainctes to haue done.</p>
               <p>Wherefore in the firſt comfortable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration,
<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the firſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</note> a man may ſay to him ſelf: thou dooſt not yet, O man, feele thine euill, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and giue thankes, that thou art not compeld to feele it: and ſo a ſmall euil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared with one that is very great, ſhall be made light and eaſie. This is that which ſome ſaye: I haue deſerued farre worſe things, yea euen hel it ſelfe: an eaſie thing ſurely to be ſpoken, but intolerable to be felt. And this euil albeit it be hid, yet doth it ſhew forth his frutes ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous:
<note place="margin">Frutes of the greateſt euill which is in man.</note> theſe are feare and the vncertainty of a trembling conſcience, whereby faith is impugned, whiles man knoweth not or douteth whether he hath God fauorable vnto him, which frute is ſo much more bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as faith is weaker. And this only infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie being wel weyed, foraſmuch as it is ſpiritual, is farre more grieuous then that of the body, which it doth make euen moſt light, being diligently compared vnto it.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6686:9"/>
               <p>Beſide theſe, to the inward euils pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all that tragedy, which the Preacher deſcribeth, whereas he ſo often maketh mention of vanitie and affliction of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. For how many counſels doe we take in vaine? how many of our deſires are fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate? how many thinges doe we ſee, how many things do we heare which we would not? Euen thoſe thinges which tende to our deſire, fall out contrary to our deſire, ſo that there is nothing entire and perfect. Moreouer all theſe thinges are ſo muche greater as one is placed in higher place or ſtate, who muſt needes be roſt with farre more and greater ſourges, waues, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, then the reſt that are troubled with the ſame thinge, ſo that the <hi>103.</hi> Pſalme ſayth well: ſmall and great beaſtes, and thinges creeping innumerable, are in the ſea of this worlde, that is, infinite ſortes of tentations, wherefore Iob chap. <hi>7.</hi> calleth the life of man a tentation. Now theſe are not therefore no euils becauſe they are litle felt, but becauſe through vſe and daily cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome they are nothing accounted of, and affliction &amp; opinion in theſe is worne out, by the worke of God: wherefore thoſe that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6686:10"/>be rare doe rather moue, which as yet we haue by no vſe learned to contemne. So that it is true, that we doe feele ſcarce the thouſandth part of our euills: it is alſo true that out euills are meaſured, felt, or not felt, not by the veritie of the thinge, but by our opinion and affection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond chapter of the ſecond conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, which is of the euill to come or before a man.</head>
               <p>IT will not a litle lighten euery preſent euill, if thou turne thy mind to them that are to come, which are ſo many, ſuch, &amp; ſo great, that hereunto alone is referred that great and one of the principall affections which is called feare,
<note place="margin">Feare what it is.</note> which ſome define to be an affection of the euill to come, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the Apoſtle ſaith Rom. <hi>11:</hi> Be not hie minded but feare.
<note place="margin">The euil to come.</note> This euil is ſo much greater, as it is more vncertaine, of what ſort and how great it wilbe when it come, ſo that it is a common ſaying: There is no age to whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcabb may not come, which notwithſtanding is an euill that is wont to happen to children and infants. So that no
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6686:10"/>man is free and exempt from any euills of any man, but whatſoeuer one man ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, the ſame alſo may an other ſuffer.</p>
               <p>This is verified by the hiſtories &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies of all ages, by all the complaints of the whole world: by more then three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſorts of diſeaſes, whereby mans body may be troubled, as ſome haue well noted. If there be ſo many diſeaſes, how many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther il chaunces thinkeſt thou wil there be of other thinges, of frendes, finally of the minde it ſelfe, which is the principall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of all euills, and the onely receptacle of ſorrow and euills?</p>
               <p>Moreouer the force &amp; feeling of euils is ſo much more increaſed, by howe much the ſtate is greater &amp; more worthy, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, ignominie, &amp; all il chaunces, ſeeing that they may euen ſodenly come, muſt needes, foraſmuch as all thinges hange as it were by a ſclender thread, be feared eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry howre, no otherwiſe then that ſworde, which Dionyſe the tyran hoonge ouer the head of his gueſt.
<note place="margin">It ought greatly to comfort vs, &amp; moue vs to loue and praiſe God, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſo many euils, few or none come vnto vs.</note> Now whatſoeuer of theſe do not come, it is to be counted for aduaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, &amp; for no ſmal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort againſt that euill that chaunceth, ſo that thou art here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6686:11"/>to ſay with Ieremie: it is through the mercies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde that we are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. For whatſoeuer of them doth not chaunce, it chaunceth not, the right hand of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Higheſt letting or prohibiting it, which mightely preſerueth vs on euery ſide as it is declared in Iob, ſo that Satan and euils doe euen grudge and beare it vnpatient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they are letted and prohibited. Wherfore we ſee, how ſweetely the Lord is to be loued, as often as any thing chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vnto vs, foraſmuch as by this one euil our moſt louing father admoniſheth vs to conſider howe many euils are ready to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile vs, if he did not ſtay and let them: as if he ſayd: Satan and a huge heape of euills deſire to ſifte thee: but I haue ſet boundes to the ſea, and haue ſayd vnto it, hitherto ſhall thy ſwelling waues come,
<note place="margin">Death the moſt terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; moſt certaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil to come, yet the time of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine.</note> and here ſhall they ſtay, as he ſayth in Iob chap. 28. But none of them ſhall come, perhaps the will of God being ſo: howbeit that which of all terrible things is ſayd to be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, namely death, ſhall moſt certainely come, and nothing is more vncertaine then the hower thereof. Which euil is ſo great, that we ſee that many men had rather liue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6686:11"/>euen with all the foreſayd euils, then they being ended to dye once. And to this one the Scripture alſo, wheras it contemneth the reſt, referreth feare, ſaying: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the end and thou ſhalt neuer do amiſſe.</p>
               <p>Conſider how many meditations, howe many bookes, how many meanes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies are ordained hereunto, ſo that with the remembrance of this onely euill it is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual to fray men from ſinnes, and make the world contemptible, to lighten ſufferings and euills, and to comfort the afflicted by comparing their euills with ſo horrible &amp; great an euill, which ſhall at one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of neceſſitie come. There is no man, who would not wiſh to ſuffer all euills, if thereby he might auoide the euill of death. This the Sainctes alſo haue feared: this Chriſt ſuffered with feare and ſweat like dropps of blood. So that the diuine mercy hath bene careful to ſtrengthen &amp; comfort the weake &amp; faint harted in nothing more then in this euill as we ſhall ſee hereafter.</p>
               <p>As for Chriſtians they haue a ſpeciall and proper cauſe to feare the euill to come,
<note place="margin">VVhat euil to come Chriſtians ought to feare.</note> which exceedeth all the other euils: this is that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle ſetteth forth <hi>I.</hi> Cor.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6686:12"/>10. ſaying: Let him that thinketh he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, take heede leſt he fal. So ſlipperie is the way, ſo mighty is the enemy, being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with our owne proper ſtrength (that is, with the aydes of the fleſh &amp; of all euill affections) accompanied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infinite hands &amp; companies of the world, with delights &amp; pleaſures on the right hand, with troubles &amp; the euil wils of men on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> left, beſide that art, a thouſand wayes to hurt, ſeduce, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, whereof he is moſt kilfull. We liue ſo that we are not ſure of our good purpoſe ſo much as a moment. Cyprian ſpeaking of many ſuch things in his epiſtle of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, teacheth that death is to be wiſhed as a ſpeedy helper to auoyde theſe euils.</p>
               <p>And for the moſt part where men haue a good hart,
<note place="margin">True Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ene death, &amp; all euils, that they may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euill of ſinne.</note> &amp; duely reuolue in their minde theſe infinite perils, we ſee them, deſpiſing life and death, that is all the aforeſaide e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills, wiſh to be loſed, that they may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo loſed from this euill of ſinnes wherein they are, as we haue ſayd in the firſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and into which they may fall, whereof we ſpeake nowe. And ſurely theſe are two moſt weighty reaſons, to moue vs not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to wiſh for death, but alſo to contemne
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6686:12"/>all euills, not to beare one euil onely light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if the Lorde ſhall giue to any to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with them, for it is the gift of God to be moued with them. For what true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian will not wiſh euen to dye, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſicke, who ſeeth and feeleth, that he while he liueth in healthe, is not onely in ſinnes, and continually may and daily doth fall into moe, and ſo without intermiſſion doth contrary to the moſte louing will of his moſt louing Father? With this vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie of indignation Paule beinge mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued (as it is declared Rom. 7.) when he had complayned that he did not the good which he woulde, but the euill which he would not, cryed out: O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the bodye of this death? The grace of God ſayth he by Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c. He litle lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth God his Father, who doth not chooſe rather the euill of death, then this euill of ſinning, ſeing that he hath ordayned death hereunto that this euil may at the laſt haue an ende, and death may be the miniſter of life and righteouſnes, whereof ſhal be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:6686:13"/>
               <head>The third chapter of the third conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which is of the euill paſt or behind vs.</head>
               <p>HErein more then in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt notably ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſweete mercye of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is able to comfort vs in all our diſtreſſe.
<note place="margin">VVe shall then chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly perceiue the goodnes of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs, &amp; the care which he hath ouer vs, when we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider our life paſt.</note> For euery man neuer feeleth the hand of God more preſent vpon him, then when he calleth to minde the yeares of his life paſt. Sainct Auguſtine ſaith: If a man ſhould chooſe either to dye, or to leade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine his life paſt, he would chooſe rather to die, conſidering ſo great perills &amp; euils, which he hath ſcarce and hardely auoided. Which ſaying is moſt true, if it be well &amp; duely weyed. For here a man may ſee, how often he hath without his owne ſtudye, without his owne care, yea without and contrary to his deſire, done and ſuffered many thinges, whereof he did not ſo much as thinke before they were done, or in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the worke being ended, he is then firſt compelled to ſay: Howe hath it come to paſſe that I haue done theſe thinges, which I did not thinke on, or thought of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6686:13"/>thinges? ſo that the prouerbe is true: Man purpoſeth, but God diſpoſeth, that is, altereth, and bringeth to paſſe an other thinge then man purpoſeth, that euen in this one thinge we can not denie, that our life and actions are gouerned &amp; directed, not by our owne wiſedom, but by the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous power, counſel, &amp; goodnes of God. Hereby we perceiue howe often God hath bene w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, when we neither ſaw nor felt it, and how truely Peter ſayd: Caſt all your care on him, for he careth for you.</p>
               <p>Wherfore if there were no bookes nor ſermons, yet our life it ſelfe led through ſo many euills and perills, if it be well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, doth abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly commend the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God to be preſent with vs, &amp; moſt ſweete vnto vs, who hath farre otherwiſe then we either thought or felt, borne vs as it were in his boſome, and as Moſes ſayth Deut. 32: The Lord hath kept him as the apple of his eye, he hath led him about, and caried him on his ſhoulders. And hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on came thoſe ſayinges in the Pſalter: I remember the time paſt, I meditate in all thy works, yea I do meditate in the works of thy handes: I will remember the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6686:14"/>of olde: And againe: I remembred thy iudgements of old,
<note place="margin">VVe ought greatly to be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the preſent euil when we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider from how many euills God hath preſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued vs in our life paſt</note> and haue bene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. All theſe and ſuch like tende to this ende, that we ſhould knowe, that if we ſee that God was then preſent with vs, when we did not thinke thereof, neither he did ſeeme to be preſent, we ſhoulde not doubt that he is nowe alſo preſent, when he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto vs to be abſent. For he that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and preſerued vs in many neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties without our owne care or thinkinge thereof, he I ſaye will not forſake vs in a ſmall matter although he ſeeme to forſake vs, according as he ſayth in Eſai: A litle while haue I forſaken thee, but with great mercifulnes ſhall I take thee vnto me. Hereunto thou mayſt adde: Who hath had care of vs ſo many nightes when we flept? who was carefull for vs as often as we la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored, plaied, and did infinite other things, wherein we were nothing carefull for our ſelues?</p>
               <p>So we ſee how al our care, whether we will or no,
<note place="margin">VVhy God leaueth vs ſometime to our owne care, he him ſelfe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming not to care for vs.</note> muſt be referred to God alone, we being very ſeldom left to our owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell or care, which notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſometime doth, that he may teach vs to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6686:14"/>his goodnes, that we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue howe muche difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his care and ours. Wherefore he ſometime ſuffereth ſome light ſicknes or other euil to come vnto vs, making ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath no care of vs (for in deede there is no time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he careth not for vs) notwithſtanding he doth in the meane ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon prohibit &amp; let, that ſo many euils as are ready to aſſaile vs, do not together on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide come viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vpon vs, that he may try vs as moſt deare children whether we will commit our ſelues to his care being knowne of vs through all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of our life, &amp; marke how vnprofitable &amp; impotent our owne care is. For what doe we profit our ſelues, or what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we profit our ſelues in al our life, who in a litle while can not cure &amp; remedie one onely payne of the legge?</p>
               <p>Why then are we ſo careful in the point of one perill or euill, and doe not leaue the care to him, when as our life it ſelfe being witnes, we are kept and preſerued in ſo many euills without our owne labour or trauel? To know &amp; duely to conſider theſe things, is to know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of God, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate in his workes, &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remembrance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6686:15"/>of them to be comforted in aduerſitie and troubles: But they that are ignorant here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall fall into that which is mentioned Pſal. 29. Becauſe they haue not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the workes of the Lord, nor the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his handes, thou ſhalt breake them downe, and not build them vp. For they are vnthankful for all the care which God hath taken for them in all their life, who do not commit the care of them ſelues to him for a litle while.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourth chapter of the fourth conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which is of the euill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath vs.</head>
               <p>AS yet we haue ſeene no other in all the euills which we ſuffer, but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God is ſo great, and ſo preſent with vs, that among innumerable euills, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are compaſſed in this life, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are euen impriſoned, ſcarce a very few, and thoſe not at all times are ſuffered to aſſaile vs, ſo that euery preſent euill wherewith we are troubled, is but an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertizement of certaine great aduauntage, which we haue through the goodnes of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6686:15"/>God, whiles that he ſuffereth vs not to be oppreſſed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of euills wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are compaſſed. For it is a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, if one be aſſailed with infinit blowes, &amp; be touched but with one alone, yea it is a grace that he is not ſtricken with all, a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle that he is not ſtricken with many.</p>
               <p>Nowe the firſt of the euills that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath vs, is death, the ſecond, hell.
<note place="margin">The euills beneath vs what they are, &amp; how we may take comfort by the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the firſt of them.</note> If we conſider the ſhamefull and vile death of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wherewith ſinners are puniſhed, we ſhall eaſily perceiue with howe great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage we ſuffer leſſe then we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. For how many are hanged, drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or ſtricken with the ſword, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes haue done farre leſſer ſinnes then we, ſo that their death and miſerie is ſette before vs of Chriſt as a glaſſe, wherein we maye ſee what we haue deſerued: as Luke 13. when certaine ſhewed him of the Galileans, whoſe bloode Pilace had mingled with their ſacrifices, he aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: ſuppoſe ye that theſe Galileans were greater ſinners then the other Galileans, becauſe they haue ſuffered ſuche thinges? I tell you, nay: but except ye amend your liues, ye ſhal all likewiſe periſh. Or thinke
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6686:16"/>you that thoſe eighteene, vpon whom the tower in Siloam fell, and ſlue them, were ſinners aboue all men that dwell in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem? I tel you, nay: but except ye amend your liues, ye ſhal all likewiſe periſh. For we may not thinke that leſſer euils are due vnto vs, who haue committed greater or like ſinnes. Neither will the iuſtice and truth of God be vniuſt &amp; falſe for vs, who hath determined to giue to euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deedes.</p>
               <p>Moreouer,
<note place="margin">How we may take comfort by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the ſecond euill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath vs.</note> in hell, &amp; eternal damnation howe many thouſand are there, who haue not committed the thouſandth part of our ſinnes? how many virgins are there, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; they whom we call innocents? how many religious men, Prieſtes, &amp;c. who in their whole life ſemed to ſerue God, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happs through ſome one fall are puniſhed for euer? Here muſt be no diſſembling: the iuſtice of God is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in euery ſinne, he hateth &amp; condemneth ſinne alike in whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be found. Doe we not here ſee the ineſtimable mercy of God, which hath not condemned them who haue ſo often deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it? Howe muche, I praye you, is it which we can ſuffer euen in all our life, in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6686:16"/>reſpect of the eternall puniſhment, which they ſuffer hauing deſerued it perhaps by one offence, we in the meane time being free, and ſaued from many ſinnes which God paſſeth ouer and remitteth? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we do not regard theſe benefits of God, or make light accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of them, it is through vnthankfulnes &amp; a certaine ſenſeles hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of incredulitie.</p>
               <p>Hereunto moreouer are to be referred ſo many Infidels, Gentiles, Iewes, vnto whom if thoſe things had ben giuen which are giuen to vs, they had bene, not in hell, but in heauen, and had farre leſſe ſinned. Examples hereof Chriſt ſetteth before our eyes Matth. <hi>II.</hi> ſaying: Wo be to thee Corazin: Wo be to thee Bethſaida: for if the greate workes which were done in you, had bene done in Tyrus and Sidon, they had repented long agone in ſackcloth &amp; aſhes: but I ſay to you, it ſhalbe eaſier for Tyrus &amp; Sidon at the day of iudgement, then for you. And thou Capernaum which art lifted vp vnto heauen, ſhalt be brought downe to hell: for if the greate workes which haue bene done in thee, had bene done among them of Sodom, they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6686:17"/>to this day: but I ſay vnto you, that it ſhal be eaſier for them of the land of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the day of iudgement, then for thee. We ſee therefore what great praiſe &amp; loue we owe to our moſt gracious God, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry euill of this life, for that we caſt ſcarce of one drop of them which we haue deſerued, which Iob compareth to the ſea, and to the ſande of the ſea.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The fift chapter of the fift conſideration, which is of the euill on the left hand.</head>
               <p>HEre we muſt ſet before our eyes that great companie of aduerſaries and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill men,
<note place="margin">The firſt comfort which the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the euill on the left hand miniſtreth vnto vs.</note> &amp; in them we muſt firſt conſider, that they haue not done that euil to our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, fame, ſoules, which they would haue done, but that God did ſtay and let them: and the higher calling and ſtate that one is placed in, to ſo many more deceits, ſubtle deuiſes, ſclaunders and troubles of the aduerſaries is he ſubiect, in all which he may perceiue &amp; feele the preſent hande of God. What maruell is it then if we be ſometime touched with ſome one?</p>
               <p>Secondly their owne euills are to be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6686:17"/>conſidered of vs alſo,
<note place="margin">The ſecond comfort which we may take by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill on the left hand.</note> not that we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice at them, but that we ſhould haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on them. Nowe they alſo are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to all the ſame euils, whereunto we are ſubiect, as it may be eaſily perceiued by the former co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations. Howbeit herein they are more miſerable then we, that they are out of our ſocietie, as well corporall as ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. For this euil which we ſuffer is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in compariſon of that, that they liue in ſinnes, in infidelitie, vnder the wrath of God, vnder the dominion of the deuil, moſt miſerable ſlaues of vngodlines and ſinne, ſo that if the whole worlde ſhoulde curſe them, it coulde wiſhe them no worſe. All which if we doe throughly perceiue, we ſhall alſo perceiue, with how great fauour and bleſſing of God we, liuing in faith, in the kingdome of Chriſt, in the ſeruice of God, do ſuffer ſome litle euill of the body, which in ſo great plentie of moſt excellent thinges, ſhould not be ſo much as felt: yea their miſerie ought to be ſo grieuous to him that hath a Chriſtian and godly hart, that he ſhould thinke his owne griefes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes. For ſo Paule willeth Philip. <hi>2:</hi> Looke not euery man on his owne things,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6686:18"/>but euery man on the things of other men. Let the ſame minde be in you, that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in Chriſt Ieſus, who being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of God, tooke on him the forme of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, &amp;c. That is, with moſt louing affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he tooke on him our forme, behauing him ſelfe no otherwiſe in our euills, then if they had bene his owne, ſo, as it were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting his owne good thinges, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him ſelfe of no reputation, that he might be found altogether made like vnto men, refuſing to be ſubiect to no humane thinge, being occupied onely in our euills.</p>
               <p>The Saincts being animated by this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and by this example ſtirred vp, are wont to pray euen for the euills of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, &amp; to do all things according to the example of Chriſt, &amp; forgetting their owne iniuries or righteouſnes, to be careful how they may deliuer them from their euills, wherwith they are w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out compariſon more troubled then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their owne, as Peter wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of Lot 2. Pet. 2, who dwelled among them, which vexed his righteous ſoule from day to day w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their vnlawfull deedes.</p>
               <p>Thou ſeeſt therefore how deepe a pit of euils here appeareth, &amp; that we haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6686:18"/>to take pity and compaſſion, &amp; to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our owne ſmall euil, if the loue of God be in vs: thou ſeeſt alſo how litle God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth vs to ſuffer in reſpect of thoſe thinges which they ſuffer.
<note place="margin">VVhy the euills of our aduerſaries and euill men do litle moue vs.</note> But whereas theſe things do litle moue vs, the cauſe is, for that the eye of the hart is not ſufficient cleare, whereby we ſhould ſee how great y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ignominie and miſerie of man is lying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinne, that is, being ſeparate from God &amp; in ſubiection vnder the deuill. For who is ſo harde harted, which is not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moued with pitie and compaſſion at the miſerable ſight of them that lye in the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Churches, &amp; in the ſtreetes, their faces being gnawne, their noſes and eyes eaten with corruption, and their other members waſted with filth and rottennes, ſo that the mind deteſteth to thinke therof, much leſſe can y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eie abide to behold it. But what doth God intend and purpoſe by theſe miſerable creatures, who haue like fleſh as we haue, &amp; are our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like vnto vs, but that he may open the eies of our mind, whereby we may ſee in how more oughly a ſort the filth and corruption of the ſoule of a ſinner appeareth, albeit he weare
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6686:19"/>purple and gold, roſes &amp; lillies, as though he were a child of Paradiſe. But how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinners are there in the world, to one of them whoſe bodies are full of ſores?</p>
               <p>Now theſe euills which are infinite as well in greatnes as in multitude, being contemned or not regarded in our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, this contempt is the cauſe that our owne euill being euen one of the leaſt ſort, ſeemeth vnto vs to be very great, and that we thinke that no other are troubled with the like.
<note place="margin">Euill men euen in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of out ward cuills are in worſe caſe then the godly.</note> But it muſt needes be that euen in outwarde euills alſo they are in worſe caſe then we. What, I pray you, can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull or throughly pleaſant vnto them, albeit they haue and enioy all thinges that they deſire, when as their conſcience can not be quiet? Is there a more grieuous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill then the trouble of a ſtinging conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? For Eſai ſayth chap. 57: The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are like the raginge ſea that can not reſt, whoſe water ſometh with the myre and grauell: euen ſo the wicked haue no peace ſayth God. Wherefore thou mayſt ſee that verified in them which is written Deut. 28: The Lord ſhall giue thee an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet hart, and daſing eyes, and ſorrowe of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6686:19"/>mind, and thy life ſhal hange in dout before thee: thou ſhalt feare both day and night, and ſhalt haue none aſſurance of thy life. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning thou ſhalt ſay, Would God it were night: and at night thou ſhalt ſay, Would God it were morning, for feare of thine hart wherewith thou ſhalt be terrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and becauſe of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſee with thine eyes.</p>
               <p>Briefly, if one did with due affection ſee and conſider all the euills of euill men, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of enemies or frendes, he woulde not onely forgette his owne euills, and ſeeme vnto him ſelfe to ſuffer nothinge, but alſo with Moſes and the Apoſtle Paule earne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly wiſhe that he might dye for them, and be raſed out of the booke of life, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from Chriſt, as it is written Rom. 9, that they might be deliuered. Chriſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with this zeale and inflamed affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on died for vs, and deſcended into hell, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs an example, that we alſo ſhould be ſo carefull for the euills of others, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting quite our owne, yea deſirous of our owne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:6686:20"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward it bringeth the quiet frute of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes vnto them which are thereby ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed. Thus much ſayth Paule.</p>
               <p>Who would not be terrified with theſe wordes of Paule, where he expreſly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that they are not the ſonnes of God, which are without the correction of God? And who can be more ſtrongly confirmed, &amp; more effectually comforted, then he that heareth that they are loued of the Lorde which are chaſtened of him, that they are ſonnes, that they haue communion with all the Sainctes, and that not they alone doe ſuffer? This vehement exhortation is able to make chaſtening and correction euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable and to be loued.
<note place="margin">There ought not therefore to be impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fering, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all ſeeme not to ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</note> Neither is here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place for excuſe, for that ſome doe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer lighter euills, ſome thoſe that be more grieuous, for euery one is tried according to meaſure, not aboue his ſtrength, as it is ſayd Pſal. 80: Thou ſhalt feede them with the bread of teares, and giue them teares to drinke with meaſure. The ſame Paule alſo ſayth: God is faithfull, which will not ſuffer you to be tempted aboue that you be able, but will euen giue the iſſue with the tentation, that ye may be able to beare it.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6686:20"/>Where therefore there is a greater euill, there are more meanes to eſcape out of tentation, and more helpe, ſo that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equalitie of ſuffering is rather in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance then in very deede.</p>
               <p>Doth not the example of Iohn Baptiſt,
<note place="margin">A notable example of the euill on the right hand, moſt diligently to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</note> whoſe feaſt we celebrate at this day that he was beheaded of Herode, greatly amaze vs all, that ſo great a man, then whome a greater hath not riſen amonge them that are begotten of women, the ſpeciall friend of the bridegrome, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forerunner of Chriſt, greater then all the Prophets, that ſuch a one I ſay, was not put to death at the leaſt by publike iudgement, was not at the leaſt accuſed of ſome fayned crime, as Chriſt was, nor for the peoples ſake, but at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the daughter of an harlot which had daunced before Herode, was beheaded in the priſon? The ignominious death of this one Sainet; and his life ſo vilely and after ſo vnworthy a ſort yeelded vp into the handes of a moſte malitious and cruell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultereſſe, ought to lighten and aſſwage all our euill. Where was God here, who might ſee ſuch things? where was Chriſt, who hearing this, did quite hold his peace?
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6686:21"/>He dieth as though he were vnknowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, men, and all creatures. What doe we ſuffer, wherein, I will not ſay we may boaſt, but not at al be troubled, if it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the death of this man? Or where ſhall we appeare, if we wil ſuffer nothing, when as ſo great men do vndeſeruedly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſo ſhamefull and ignominious death, and their bodies are mocked and ſcorned of their enemies after their death? Behold, ſayth the Lord in Ieremie, they that men thought were vmneete to drinke of the cup haue drunke with the firſt, &amp; thinkeſt thou then to be free? No no, thou ſhalt neither be quit nor free, but thou muſt drinke alſo.</p>
               <p>Rightly therfore did that Eremite,
<note place="margin">A ſingular example of an Eremite</note> who when he had bene ſicke euery yeare, being at the laſt one whole yeare in health, was very ſorrowfull, and wept bitterly, ſaying that God had forgotten him, &amp; denied vnto him his grace. So neceſſary and wholſom is the chaſtiſing of the Lorde to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.
<note place="margin">The ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the Saincts ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table being wel conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore we ſhal ſee that it is litle or nothing which we ſuffer, if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how the Sainctes were thruſt vnder the nayles with ſharpe pricks, how they were impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6686:21"/>ſlaine with the ſword, burned, torne in peeces w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wild beaſts, &amp; ſuffered infinite torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: yea if we doe but wey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tentations of them which are preſent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs in this life, and ſuffer moſt grieuous perſecutions of the deuill. For there are which ſuffer more ſharpely and grieuouſly then we doe, as well in ſpirit as in body.</p>
               <p>Some ſay here: This I lament, that my ſuffering is not comparable to the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of the Saincts, becauſe I am a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, &amp; not worthy to be compared w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. They ſuffered for their innocencie, I ſuffer for my ſinnes, wherfore it is no maruell if they ſuffered all things cheerefully.
<note place="margin">Our ſinnes ought not to hinder vs from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the ſufferings of the Sainctes.</note> This is a very vnwiſe ſaying. For if thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for thy ſinnes, thou muſt reioyce, that thy ſinnes are ſcoured: were not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saincts alſo ſinners? But feareſt thou that thou art like Herode &amp; the theefe on the left hande? Thou art not, if thou be patient: for what made difference betweene the theefe on the left hand and him on the right, but patience in faythe? If thou be a ſinner, well, the theefe was a ſinner alſo, but by patience he attained to the glory of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes and ſanctitie: which that thou maiſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6686:22"/>doe, doe likewiſe as he did. For thou canſt not ſuffer but thou ſhalt ſuffer either for ſinnes, or for righteouſnes: either ſuffering doth ſanctifie and make bleſſed, if thou loue it, and ſuffer in faith: wherefore there is no excuſe remaining. Finally as ſoone as thou haſt faithfully confeſſed that thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſuffer iuſtely for thy ſinnes, thou art righteous and holy, as the theefe on the right hande. For the confeſſion of ſinne, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it is of faith, doth iuſtifie and make holy, and ſo in a moment after ſuche confeſſion thou dooſt not ſuffer for ſinnes, but for innocencie: for he that is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doth not ſuffer but innocently: but thou art become righteous after faithfull confeſſion of thy worthy ſuffering, and of thy ſinnes. Wherefore thy ſuffering may truely and worthely be compared to the ſufferinges of the Sainctes, euen as thy confeſſion of thy ſinnes may truely and worthely be compared to the confeſſion of them: for there is one faith of all, one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſinnes, one ſuffering of euils, and one true communion of Saincts in all and through all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:6686:22"/>
               <head>The ſeuenth chapter of the ſeuenth conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, which is of the euill aboue vs.</head>
               <p>LAſtly we muſt lift vp our hart on hie, &amp; aſcend vp the mountaine of myrre with the ſpouſe. Here is Ieſus Chriſt crucified,
<note place="margin">The euil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue vs, &amp; the comfort which the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof miniſtreth.</note> the head of all the Sainctes, the chiefe of all that ſuffer. The memory of him is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the ſpouſe, where it is ſayd: Set me as a ſeale vpon thine hart, &amp; as a ſignet vpon thine arme. The blood of this lambe beinge ſtriken on the poſtes, ſuffereth not the angell the deſtroyer to approch. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is the ſpouſe commended, that her heare is like purple (that is, her meditation is red by the memorie of Chriſtes paſſion.) This is the tree which Moſes was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to caſt into the waters of Marah, that is, bitter paſſions, &amp; they were made ſweete. There is nothing that this paſſion doth not make ſweete, euen death, as the ſpouſe ſayth: His lippes are like lillies,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cantic.</hi> 5.14</note> that droppe pure myrrhe. Nowe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this likenes of lillies and lippes, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as theſe are red, &amp; thoſe are white,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6686:23"/>ſurely ſhe ſpeaketh myſtically, that the words of Chriſt are moſt gentle and pure, wherein is no cruell bitternes or ſpite, but are ſweete and mylde, which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding droppe and perſwade pure and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall myrre (that is moſt bitter death.) Theſe moſt pure &amp; ſweete lippes are able to make moſt bitter death (which as pure myrre taketh away at once all the ſtincke of ſinne) ſweete, mild, gentle, &amp; acceptable. How ſhal this come to paſſe? Euen while thou heareſt that Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, hath by his moſt holy ſuffering conſecrated &amp; made holy all paſſions, euen death it ſelf, hath bleſſed malediction, hath glorified ignominie, hath enriched pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. So that death is compelled to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gate of life, malediction the beginning of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes, ignominie the way to glory. Now how canſt thou be ſo hard harted &amp; vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that thou wouldeſt not euen wiſh for &amp; loue all the paſſions which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt pure and holy fleſh and blood of Chriſt are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, made harmeles, wholſom, bleſſed and happy vnto thee?</p>
               <p>For if by the touching of his moſt pure fleſh he hath ſanctified all waters to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6686:23"/>how much more by the touching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame his moſt pure fleſh and blood, hath he ſanctified all death, all ſufferings, all iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, all ſclaunders, all ignominie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of the ſpirit or blood? as he ſayth of the ſame baptiſme of ſuffering Luke 12: I muſt be baptiſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a baptiſme, &amp; howe am I grieued till it be ended? Thou ſeeſt how he is diſquieted, how he is grieued, how he thirſteth to ſanctifie &amp; make amiable, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions &amp; death. For he ſaw that we were ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paſſions, he ſaw that we did great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare &amp; dread death. Therfore as a moſt louing ſhepeheard, and faithfull phiſition, minding to moderate this euil, he maketh haſt &amp; with griefe deſireth to die, &amp; by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſame vnto vs.
<note place="margin">The death of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> So that the death of a Chriſtian is to be counted like the braſen ſerpent that Moſes ſet vp, which in euery reſpect reſembled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of a ſerpent, but was wholy without life, without motion, without venim, without ſtinging: ſo the righteous ſeeme in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes of the vnwiſe to die, but they are in peace. We are like to them that die, neither doth our death appeare any otherwiſe then the death of others, notwithſtanding it is an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6686:24"/>other thinge, for death is deade vnto vs. So alſo all our other ſufferinges are like the ſufferings of others, howbeit in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance onely, but in very deede our ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings are the beginnings of reſt, as death is the beginning of life. And this is that which Chriſt ſayth Iohn 8: If a man keepe my worde he ſhall neuer ſee death. Howe commeth it to paſſe that he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee it? becauſe he dying, beginneth to liue, ſo by reaſon of the life which he ſeeth, he can not ſee death. For here the night ſhineth as the day, for that the light of the life beginning is more cleare, then of the death ending. Theſe thinges are certaine to all them that beleeue in Chriſt, but to them that doe not beleeue they are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if thou wouldeſt kiſſe, loue and embrace the coate of Chriſt, the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, waterpots, and whatſoeuer thinges Chriſt hath touched, and which he hath v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for moſt ſweete relicks, as conſecrated by his touching &amp; vſing them: why dooſt thou not much more loue, embrace &amp; kiſſe paynes, troubles of the world, ignominie and death, not only conſecrated by his tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6686:24"/>but alſo embrued and bleſſed with his moſt precious blood, moreouer embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> harty wil and exceeding loue, which vehemently moued him thereunto? eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in theſe thou haſt farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter benefits, rewards &amp; good things, then in thoſe relicks. For by theſe thou obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt victory of death and hell, and of all thy ſinnes, and not by them, O, if a man might haue beheld the hart of Chriſt, when han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe he was diſtreſſed, that he might make death dead &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible, how earneſtly &amp; ſweetely he embraced death &amp; paines for the fearfull and them that dread death &amp; paynes, how willingly he droonke of this cup to the ſicke, that we alſo might not be afraide to drinke thereof, while we ſee that no euill, but onely good came vnto him by riſinge againe: without doubt it would be pure myrre, diſtilling from his lippes, moſte pleaſaunt and ſweete, as the ſauour and goodlines of the lillies. Hereof ſpeaketh Peter in his firſt Epiſtle and 4. chapter: Foraſmuch as Chriſt hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs in the fleſhe, arme your ſelues likewiſe with the ſame mynde. And Paule ſayth Hebr. 12: Conſider him that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6686:25"/>ſuche ſpeaking againſt of ſinners, leaſt ye ſhould be wearied &amp; faint in your mindes.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if in the former conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are of things ſet as yet beneath vs or by vs, we haue learned to ſuffer euill patiently: ſurely by this laſt, which is of that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is now aboue &amp; not by vs, we lifting vp our harts vnto Chriſt, and being made victors ouer all euills,
<note place="margin">VVhat af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the euill aboue vs ought to breede in vs.</note> are taught not onely to ſuffer them, but to loue, wiſhe, ſeeke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the farther a man is of from this affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, of ſo much leſſe force is the croſſe of Chriſt in him, as it is in them that vſe the ſigne of the croſſe, and Chriſtes paſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euills and death, that they may not ſuffer nor die, endeuoring to attaine vnto that which is quite contrary to the croſſe and death of Chriſt. Wherefore in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth conſideration it muſt needes be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp and conſumed, whatſoeuer euill we ſuffer, ſo that now it doe not onely not grieue, but alſo delight, howbeit if this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration perſe the hart, &amp; be fixed in the inward affection of the mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus much concerning the former table: the latter followeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:6686:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VVE will deuide the ſecond table into ſeuen conſiderations alſo, contrary to the former: whereof the firſt ſhall be of the inward good: The ſecond of that which is to come: The thirde of that which is paſte: The fourth of that which is beneath vs: The ſift of that which is on the left hande: The ſixt of that which is on the right hande: The ſeuenth of that which is aboue vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>THE FIRST CHAPTER of the firſt conſideration, which is of the inward good.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho is able to number euen thoſe good thinges onely which euery one poſſeſſeth in his one perſon?
<note place="margin">The giftes of the body</note> Firſt how many are the giftes of the bodye? as beautie, ſtrength, health, quicknes of ſenſe, whereunto in the male kinde may be added the moſte noble ſex, whereby he is fit to doe many things both
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6686:26"/>priuate and publike, and to atchieue many notable exploytes,
<note place="margin">How we may take comfort by conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the giftes of the body.</note> whereunto a woman is vnapt. Nowe what a great matter is it, if by the bleſſing of God thou enioyeſt theſe excellent gifts ten, twenty, thirty yeares w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pleaſure, &amp; at the laſt art troubled in ſome one of them for the ſpace of ten daies? It is a common ſaying among notorious offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: It is but one ill howres matter, and agayne, A good howre is worth an ill howre. What ſhal be ſayd of vs, who enioy many good howres, and wil not ſuffer euil ſo much as one howre? We ſee therefore in how great plenty we enioy the benefits of God, and with how fewe euills we are ſcarce touched, at the leaſt the moſt of vs. Our moſt gratious God not content with theſe good thinges, giueth moreouer ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, abundance of all things, if not to all, ſurely to many, and to them eſpecially that are weake to beare euills. For as I haue ſayd before, vpon whom he beſtoweth leſſe riches, or giftes of the body, vpon them he beſtoweth more giftes of the mind, that all thinges may be equall, &amp; he a iuſt iudge of all. For abundance of riches doth not ſo much comfort as a ioyful mind. Moreouer
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6686:26"/>he giueth vnto ſome goodly children, great pleaſure, power, rule, honour, fame, glory, fauour, &amp;c. which if he permitte to enioy a long time, yea but a ſmall time, they will eaſily admoniſh what is to be done in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle euill.</p>
               <p>But the giftes of the mind are more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then all theſe, as witte, knowledge,
<note place="margin">How we may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the giftes of the mind.</note> iudgement, eloquence, wiſedom, &amp; as in the other, ſo in beſtowing of theſe he vſeth a meane and equalitie, ſo that vpon whom he hath beſtowed more of theſe good thinges, he hath not therfore preferred them before others, whom in ſteede of theſe he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen more peace or pleaſure of the minde. Nowe in all theſe we muſt with thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes acknowledge the large liberalitie and bountifulnes of God, &amp; comfort our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that in the multitude &amp; plenty of good things we do not meruel, if ſome ſharpenes be mingled therwith, ſeeing that to delicat perſons neither roſtedmeate is liked with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſauce, neither almoſt any other meate, which eyther hath not ſome ſharpe taſte of it ſelfe, or is tempered with ſome thinge that hath a ſharpe taſte: ſo vntolerable a thinge is continuall and onely ſweetenes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6686:27"/>that one ſayde rightly: All pleaſure by continuance maketh it ſelfe lotheſome. And an other ſaid: Pleaſure it ſelfe at the laſt is a labour, euen becauſe this life is more weake, then that it is able without the temperature of euills, to enioy onely good thinges, by reaſon of the ouermuch aboundance of good thinges, whereupon hath riſen this prouerbe, The bones muſt be ſtronge which ſhall beare good dayes, which prouerbe I oftentimes conſidering do greatly maruell what a maruelous and true meaning it hath, that mens minds are contrary to them ſelues, who ſeke no other but good dayes, which notwithſtanding when they haue obtained, they can worſe away with them then with euill.</p>
               <p>Now what other thinge are we taught hereby, but that euen in the very enemies of the croſſe, the croſſe is maruelous, ſo that by the meanes thereof all ought to be tempered and ſanctified leaſt they periſh, as fleſh muſt be ſeaſoned with ſalt, leſt it ſtincke and corrupt.</p>
               <p>Why then doe we not moſt willingly receiue this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perature ſent of God, which if he ſhould not ſend, our life which is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6686:27"/>continually to ſuffer pleaſures &amp; good thinges, woulde procure it of it owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde? We ſee therefore howe truely the wiſe man ſaid of God: He reacheth from one ende to an other mightely, and louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth he order all things. If we through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider theſe thinges, that alſo will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be true which Moſes ſaith Deut. <hi>32:</hi> He hath borne him on his ſhoulders, he hath caried him about, and kept him as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apple of his eye. Hereby we may ſtoppe the mouthes of them which vnthankefully babble that there are more euill then good thinges in this life, when as there are not wanting infinite good thinges and ſweete commodities, but they are wanting which ſhould ſee &amp; acknowledge them with him that ſayd: The earth is full of the goodnes of the Lorde. And agayne: The earth is full of his prayſe. And Pſal. <hi>103:</hi> The earth is full of thy riches: thou haſt made me glad by thy workes. Hereupon we dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinge: Heauen and earth are full of thy glory. Why ſo? becauſe there are many good thinges whereby he may be prayſed, howbeit of them onely which ſee and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this fulnes. For as we haue
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6686:28"/>ſayd in the firſt conſideration of euils, that the euills of euery one are ſo great, as is his opinion &amp; knowledge of them: ſo alſo good thinges although they come vnto vs abundantly on euery ſide, yet are they only ſo great as they are eſtemed. For al things that God hath made are exceeding good, yet are they not ſo acknowledged of all, as of them of whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>103.</hi> Pſalme ſpeaketh: They contemned that pleaſant lande.</p>
               <p>Of this conſideration we may in Iob ſee a moſt goodly &amp; ſingular example,
<note place="margin">Iob may be a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to moue vs patiently to ſuffer euills if the Lord ſend them, ſeeing we receiue ſo many good thinges at his hande.</note> who, all his goods being take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, ſaid: Shal we receiue good at the hande of God, &amp; not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue euil? a very golden ſaying, &amp; a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty comfort in tentation. For he did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer him ſelfe, but was tempted of his owne wife to impatiencie, who ſayde vnto him: Dooſt thou continue yet in thy perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctnes? curſe God &amp; die: as if ſhe ſhould ſay: It is manifeſt that he is not God, who hath ſo forſaken thee, why therefore dooſt thou truſt in him, &amp; not rather denying and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him, acknowledgeſt thy ſelfe mortall, vnto whom nothing ſhal remaine after this life? Theſe &amp; ſuch like thinges doth euery mans wife, that is his ſenſuality &amp; corrupt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6686:28"/>vnderſtanding put into his mind in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of tentation, becauſe the ſenſe ſauoureth not the things that are of God.</p>
               <p>Howbeit theſe are good things common to all:
<note place="margin">The inward good things of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> but a Chriſtian is endued with farre better inward good things, as with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of Chriſt, wherof is ſpoken Pſal. <hi>44:</hi> The Kings daughter is al glorious within, her clothing is of broidered golde. For as we haue ſaid entreating of the conſideration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt euill, that there can be none ſo great euil felt in man, which is the worſt of thoſe euils that are in him: ſo the beſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good things that are in a Chriſtian he him ſelfe can not ſe. For if he did, he ſhould be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in heauen, foraſmuch as the kingdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Chriſt ſaith, is within vs. For to haue faith is to haue the truth &amp; word of God: to haue the worde of God is to haue God the maker of all things. Which good thinges howe great are they? if they were reuealed to the minde, it ſhoulde in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be loſed from the bodye, by reaſon of exceeding ſweetenes and pleaſure: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other good things that we haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of are rightly ſaid to be as it were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain aduertizements of thoſe good things,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6686:29"/>which we haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in, which God will haue commended vnto vs by them, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this life can not ſuffer that they ſhould be reuealed, and therfore God mercifully hideth them, vntill they haue increaſed vnto their full meaſure: no otherwiſe then louing parents doe ſometime gyue vnto their children trifles or thinges of ſmall value, thereby to allure their mindes to hope for greater.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding they doe ſometimes ſhew out and put forth them ſelues,
<note place="margin">Frutes of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t good thinge in man.</note> when the ioyfull conſcience reioyceth in truſt in God, willingly ſpeaketh of him, heareth his word with delight and pleaſure, is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and cherefull to ſerue him, to doe good works, to ſuffer euils, &amp;c. All which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible tokens of an infinite and incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable treaſure hidden within, which diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth forth theſe litle droppes in ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: although it ſometime commeth to paſſe that it is more manifeſtly reuealed to mindes that are giuen to diuine contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> being as it were in a traunce, they can not tell where they are. Such were Auguſtin and his mother as they confeſſe of them ſelues, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:6686:29"/>
               <head>The ſecond chapter of the ſecond conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, which is of the good to come or before a man.</head>
               <p>TO them that are not Chriſtians litle comfort can be giuen in their euills by the good things to come, for that al things be to them vncertaine. Howbeit that nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affection which is called hope, is here cauſe of great trouble.
<note place="margin">Vncertaine hope.</note> By which affection men comfort them ſelues and bid one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hope for better thinges, whereby we vncertainely ſeeke after great thinges, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the moſt part deceiued, as Chriſt teacheth of that man in the Goſpell Luke <hi>12,</hi> who ſayd: I wil pul downe my barnes, and builde greater, and therein will I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all my frutes and my goods: and I will ſay to my ſoule: ſoule, thou haſt much goods layde vppe for many yeares, liue at eaſe, eate, drinke and be merie. But God ſaid vnto him, O foole, this night will they fetch away thy ſoule from thee, then whoſe ſhall thoſe thinges be which thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided? So is he that gathereth riches to him ſelfe, and is not rich in God.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:6686:30"/>
               <p>Howbeit God leaueth not the children of men ſo,
<note place="margin">God doth not alwayes ſuffer our vncertaine hope to be fruſtrate, &amp; why.</note> but in this affection to put away euill and attayne that which is good he comforteth them: albeit they be vncertaine of the thinges to come, yet doe they hope well, whereby in the meane while they are ſuſteyned, leſt that falling into the euill of deſperation, they ſuffer not the preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and ſo doe worſe thinges. Wherefore euen the affection of ſuch hope is the gifte of God, not that he will haue them truſt vnto it, but be moued to ſounde and true hope which is in him alone. For he is therefore ſlow to anger that he may bring them to repentance, as it is ſayde Rom. <hi>2:</hi> neyther doth he ſuffer men to be decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by this deceitefull hope, if ſo be that they beginne from the hart and truely to hope in him.</p>
               <p>But to Chriſtians, beſide theſe good things, two ſortes of eſpeciall good things ſhal aſſuredly come, howbeit by death and ſufferinges. Now they alſo reioyce in that common vncertain hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the preſent euill ſhall ende, &amp; the contrary good ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, although they doe not ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that, as they doe that their owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6686:30"/>good is increaſed, which is truth in Chriſt, wherein they goe forwarde from day to day, for which they both liue &amp; hope.
<note place="margin">Chriſtians receiue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of two eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall good thinges to come, wher of one is, that by death their afflictions of this life being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they ſhall be in reſt and peace.</note> But beſide theſe I haue ſayd that two eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall good thinges ſhall come vnto them in deathe. The firſt is, that by deathe the whole tragedie of the euills of this life is ended, as it is written: Precious in the ſight of the Lord is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of his Saincts. And againe: I will lay me downe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſleepe in peace. Againe: Though the righteous be preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with death, yet ſhal he be in reſt. Whereas contrariwiſe to the wicked death is the beginning of euils, as the Pſalmiſt ſayth: The death of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is very euill. Againe, Euils ſhal come vppon the wicked man in deſtruction: ſo Lazarus ſhall be comforted, who hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his euills here, whereas the riche glutton ſhall be tormented, who hath here enioyed his pleaſures. So it commeth to paſſe, that a Chriſtian whether he dye or liue, hath alwayes the better: ſo bleſſed a thinge is it to be a Chriſtian, and to beleue in Chriſt, whereupon Paule ſaith: Chriſt is to me life, &amp; death is to me aduauntage. And Rom. <hi>14.</hi> he ſayth: Whether we liue,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6686:31"/>we liue vnto the Lord: or whether we die, we die vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord: whether we liue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or die, we are the Lordes. This ſafety Chriſt hath obtained for vs, inaſmuch as he dyed and roſe agayne that he might be Lord of the liuing and dead, being able to make vs quiet and ſafe as well in life as in death, as the <hi>22.</hi> Pſalme ſayth: Though I walke through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will feare no euill, for thou art with me. If this commoditie of death doe litle moue vs, it is a ſigne that the faith of Chriſt is weake in vs, which doth not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently eſteeme the treaſure and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a good death, or doth not yet beleue that death is good, the olde man which as yet liueth too much, &amp; the wiſedome of the fleſhe hindering vs. We muſt endeuour therefore that we may know and loue this benefit of death. It is a great matter that death which to others is exceeding euill, ſhoulde be made to vs exceeding good and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious. And if Chriſt had not brought this to paſſe for vs, what thinge ſhould he haue done worthy of ſo great a price as he payed? It is a very diuine worke which he did, and therefore it ſhould be no maruel to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6686:31"/>any, that he made the euill of death excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding good.</p>
               <p>Wherefore death is nowe deade to the faithful, and hath nothing terrible but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a certaine ſemblance and appearance.
<note place="margin">Death can not hurte the faithful</note> No otherwiſe then a ſerpent that is ſlaine, in outwarde forme and appearance he is cerrible as before, but in very deede it is onely a ſeeming or appearance of euil, the euill it ſelfe is nowe dead and harmeleſſe. Yea as in the <hi>21.</hi> chapter of Numb. God commaunded a braſen ſerpent to be ſet vp, by the ſight wherof the liuing ſerpents did periſh: ſo alſo our death by faithfull and ſtedfaſt beholding of the death of Chriſt, doth periſh, and onely appeareth terrible, but can not hurt vs in very deede. So doth the mercye of God aforehande exerciſe vs that are weake, with theſe goodly figures or ſemblances, that foraſmuch as death ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be taken away, he may at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt make the force thereof to be nothing but in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew and appearance only, for which cauſe alſo death in the Scriptures is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſleepe rather then death.</p>
               <p>The other good thing that commeth by death, is, that it doth not onely ende the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6686:32"/>troubles and afflictions of this life,
<note place="margin">The other ſpecial good thinge to come, the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherof is comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to Chriſtians.</note> but which is more exccllent, it maketh an end of vices and ſinnes, which maketh death farre more acceptable to the faithfull, as we haue ſayd before, then the good which we haue nowe ſpoken of. For the euills of the ſoule which are ſinnes, are without compariſon worſe then the euills of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye. Which onely if we did knowe, they would make death moſt amiable vnto vs. Now if they do not ſo, it is a ſigne that we doe not ſufficiently feele nor hate the euils of our ſoule. Whereas therfore this life is moſt perilous, daungerous ſinne ſeeking to deceiue vs on euery ſide, and we can not liue without ſinne: moſte commodious death ſetteth vs free from theſe perills, and cutteth of ſinne quite from vs, whereupon in the booke of wiſedom it is ſayd in praiſe of the righteous: He pleaſed God and was beloued of him, ſo that whereas he liued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge ſinners, he tranſlated him. He was taken away leaſt wickednes ſhoulde alter his vnderſtanding, or deceit beguile his minde. For wickednes by bewitching ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuteth the thinges that are good, and the vnſtedfaſtnes of concupiſcence peruerteth
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6686:32"/>the ſimple minde (O howe true are theſe things and confirmed by daily experience? Though he was ſoone deade, yet fulfilled he much time, for his ſoule pleaſed God: therefore haſted he to take him away from wickednes.</p>
               <p>So by the mercie of God, death, which to man was the puniſhment of ſinne, is made to Chriſtians the ende of ſinne, and the beginning of life and righteouſnes. Wherefore he that loueth life and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, muſt needes, not feare, but loue deathe, which is the Miniſter of them, and meane to come vnto them: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he ſhall neuer attayne neyther to lyfe nor righteouſnes. Nowe he that can not doe this, let him praye vnto God, that he may. For therefore are we taught to ſaye, Thy will be done, becauſe we of our ſelues are not able to doe it, whoe fearinge deathe, doe loue death and ſinne rather then life and righteouſnes. For, that God ordayned deathe for the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinge of ſinne it maye hereof be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for that he enioyned deathe to Adam by and by after he had ſinned, as it were amendes of ſinnes, and that before he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6686:33"/>caſte him out of Paradiſe, that he might ſhewe vnto vs that deathe worketh no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, but all good in vs, ſeeing that it was enioyned in paradiſe as it were repentance and ſatisfaction. It is true in deede that death entred into the worlde by the malice of the Deuill, but it is to be attributed to the ſingular goodnes of God that death being ſo entred, he not onely ſuffered it not to hurt, but ordayned it euen from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thereof for the puniſhment and death of ſinne.</p>
               <p>For this he ſignified, whereas when he had firſt denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced death vnto Adam, in his commaundement that he ſhould not eate of the tree of knowledge, he afterward not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding did not holde his peace, but did againe enioyne death, &amp; tempered the rigour of his firſt denouncing, yea did not ſo much as make mention of death in any ſillable, but onely ſayde: In the ſweate of thy face ſhalt thou eate bread, till thou be turned againe into the ground, for out of it waſt thou taken: Duſt thou art, and into duſt ſhalt thou be turned again. As though he then hated death, which he would not ſo much as name, according to that ſaying:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6686:33"/>He endureth but a while in his anger, but in his fauour is life. He ſeemed in thus ſpeaking, that, vnleſſe death had bene ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboliſhing of ſinne, he woulde not ſo much as mention or name it, much leſſe enioyne it. So againſt ſinne which had wrought death, the emulation of God armeth no other thing but death it ſelfe, ſo that here thou mayſt ſee that ſaying of the Poet verified,
<note place="margin">The worker deſtroyed by his owne work: ſinne aboliſhed by death which is it owne proper frute.</note> that the worker of death doth periſhe by his owne worke, and that ſinne is deſtroyed by it owne proper frute, and is ſlayne by death which it brought forth, as the viper of her ofſpring. This is a moſt goodly ſight, to ſee how ſinne is, not by an others, but by it owne proper worke deſtroyed, ſlayne with it owne weapon, &amp; as of Goliath, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head thereof cut of with it owne ſworde. For Goliath was a figure of ſinne, a terrible Champion to all, except litle Dauid, that is, Chriſt, who alone o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame him, and cut of his heade with his owne ſworde. If therefore we meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ioyes of this power of Chriſt, and vpon the giftes of his grace, why ſhould a litle euil trouble vs, when as in ſo great an euill to come we ſee ſo great good thinges?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:6686:34"/>
               <head>The third chapter of the third conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is of the good paſt, or behind a man.</head>
               <p>THe conſideration of this good is eaſie, by the contrary conſideration of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil paſt, we thinke it ſufficient only to help him that ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider hereof.
<note place="margin">VVe are moued to the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the good paſt, that is of Gods goodnes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and to take co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, by the examples of Auguſtin Dauid, and by our own experience.</note> Herein B. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin doth excellently well in his confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where in a moſt goodly ſort he rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefits of God beſtowed vpon him from his mothers wombe. The ſame doth Dauid in that notable <hi>138.</hi> Pſalme, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning wherof is: O Lord, thou haſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, where among other things wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouidence of God ouer him, he ſayth: Thou vnderſtandeſt my thoughts long before: thou compaſſeſt my paths &amp; my lying downe. As if he ſayd: Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I haue euer thought, whatſoeuer I haue wrought, and whatſoeuer I was to obtayne or poſſeſſe, I ſee now, how it was not done by mine owne induſtry, but ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by thy care long before. Finally thou haſt foreſeene all my wayes: and there is not a word in my tongue, where then? euen in thy power. Theſe thinges we learne by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6686:34"/>our owne experience. For if we call to minde our life paſt, is it not a wonderful thinge that we haue thought, willed, done, and ſayd ſuch thinges, as we neuer coulde foreſee, but would haue done farre other thinges, if we had bene left to our owne free will, which we nowe firſt perceiue, namely we ſee that the hande of God hath bene ſo preſent with vs, that his care hath bene ſo conſtant ouer vs, that we could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue ſpoken, neither willed nor thought thoſe thinges which we haue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he had giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abilitie, as it is ſayd in the booke of wiſedom chap. <hi>7:</hi> In his hande are both we and our wordes. And Paule ſaythe: who worketh all thinges in vs. Why then are we not aſhamed being ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and hard harted, who being taught by our owne experience, doe ſee howe careful the Lorde hathe bene for vs vntill this howre, and hath giuen vs all good things? and yet we can not committe the ſame care of vs to him in a ſmall preſent euill, but we ſo behaue our ſelues, as thoughe he had forſaken vs, or coulde by any meanes forſake vs. Dauid did not ſo in the <hi>39.</hi> Pſalme, where he ſayeth: As for me,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:6686:35"/>him. For we ſee this moſt manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto vs commonly in all infantes, ſo that ſo many examples let forth to our fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; hardues, ought worthely to make vs greatly aſhamed, if we dout that euen the leaſt good or euill commeth vnto vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſingular care of God.
<note place="margin">VVe muſt caſt our care on God for that he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for vs.</note> Bleſſed Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſayth: Caſt all your care on him, for he careth for you. And Dauid ſayth Pſal. <hi>36:</hi> Caſt thy care vpon the Lorde, and he ſhall feede thee. Moreouer B. Auguſtine ſayth vnto his ſoule in his confeſſions: Why ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou vpon thy ſelfe and ſtandeſt not in deede? caſt thy ſelfe vpon him, for he will not withdrew his hand that thou maiſt fal. And againe Peter ſayth, <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>4:</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let them that ſuffer according to the will of God, commit their ſoules to him in wel doing, as vnto a faithfull Creator.</p>
               <p>O, if a man knew his God after this ſort, how ſecure, how quiet, how pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhould he be? Such a one ſhould haue God true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, knowing aſſuredly that all his thinges whatſoeuer they be, haue come &amp; doe come vnto him, by the direction and diſpoſing of God his moſt ſweete will. The ſaying of Peter ſtandeth certaine, he careth for you.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6686:35"/>What can we heare more ſweete &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant then this ſaying? therefore ſayth he, caſt all your care vpon him.
<note place="margin">VVhat will enſue if we caſt not our care on God.</note> If we doe not this, what doe we elſe, but endeuour to let &amp; hinder the care of God, &amp; alſo make our life vnto our ſelues troubleſom, painefull, careful, by many feares, cares &amp; troubles? and that in vaine, for we doe not any thing hereby further our reſt or quietnes, but as the Preacher in his booke ſayth: This is a vanitie of vanities, &amp; vexation of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. For in all the ſame booke he ſpeaketh of experience hereof, inaſmuch as he had tried many things for him ſelfe, and in all notwithſtanding he founde nothing but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, vanitie &amp; vexation of the ſpirit: ſo that he concludeth, that it is the gift of God, if a man eate &amp; drinke, &amp; reioice with his wife, that is, liueth without care, committing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> care of him ſelfe vnto God. Wherefore we ought to haue no other care of our ſelues, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may not be careful for our ſelues, &amp; may commit the care of vs vnto God. As for other things that might be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here, euery one may as I haue ſayd know them by the contrary conſideration, and by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to mind his whole life paſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:6686:36"/>
               <head>The fourth chapter of the fourth conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which is of the good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath vs.</head>
               <p>Hitherto we haue ſeene the good things which are our owne, and in our ſelues, we will nowe conſider thoſe that are in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and without vs: the firſt whereof is in them which are beneath vs, that is the dead and damned. Howbeit it ſeemeth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtraunge, that any good can be found in the deade and damned. But the power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine goodnes is euery where ſo great,
<note place="margin">By compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtate of the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned with our owne, we ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue the exceeding mercy of God toward vs, &amp; the ineſtimable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities which we enioy through his goodnes.</note> that it maketh that we may ſe good things euen in the greateſt euils. Now let vs firſt compare them with our ſelues, then ſhall we ſee our ineſtimable commodities, as it may eaſily be vnderſtoode by the contrary conſideration of euills. For as great euils of death and hel as we ſee in them, ſo great without dout doe we ſee our commodities to be, yea and ſo much greater, as their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills are greater. All which are not to be lightly paſſed ouer, foraſmuch as they doe greatly commende vnto vs the exceeding mercie of God. And it is to be feared, that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6686:36"/>if we make ſmall account of theſe, we ſhall be found vnthankefull, and condemned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with them, or tormented worſe, for that the more we ſee them to be grieued &amp; ſorrowfull, ſo much more ought we to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce for Gods goodnes toward vs, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that ſaying in Eſai chap. 65: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, my ſeruaunts ſhall eate, but ye ſhall haue hunger: behold, my ſeruaunts ſhall drinke, but ye ſhall ſuffer thirſt: beholde, my ſeruaunts ſhall be merie, but ye ſhallbe confounded: behold my ſeruaunts ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce for very quietnes of hart, but ye ſhal crie for ſorrowe of harte, and complayne for vexation of minde: your name ſhall ye leaue accurſed amonge my choſen, &amp;c. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally as I haue ſaid, the examples of them that die ill, and are condemned, as B. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie ſayth in a certaine Dialogue, ought to bringe this good vnto vs, that they ſhoulde admoniſhe and teach vs, that he is happye, whome other mens harmes doe make to beware. Howbeit this good, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is commonly knowne, doth litle moue vs, when as notwithſtanding it is to be counted amonge the chiefe, and is not lightly eſteemed of them that are wiſe: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6686:37"/>as a great part of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tendeth hereunto, namely where it is taught of the wrath, iudgements &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of God. Which moſt wholſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the examples of the moſt miſerable ſhould make moſt wholſom vnto vs, which then begin to be effectuall, when we are ſo affected as they are which ſuffer them, and as though we were in their place and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For then they wil moue and admoniſh vs to prayſe his goodnes, who hath preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs from thoſe thinges.</p>
               <p>Theſe dead &amp; damned muſt be compared alſo with God him ſelfe,
<note place="margin">The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the ſtate of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ought to moue vs to reioyce in God, and to praiſe &amp; extoll his iuſtice.</note> whereby we may ſee the diuine iuſtice in them. This albeit it be harde, yet muſt we endeuour to doe it. For ſeeing that God is a iuſt Iudge, his iuſtice muſte be loued and prayſed: and therfore muſt we reioice in God euen then when he deſtroyeth the euill both in body and ſoule, becauſe in all theſe his entire and vnſpeakeable iuſtice ſhineth. Wherefore hell alſo is full of God and the ſouereigne good as well as heauen. For the iuſtice of God is God himſelfe, and God is the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne good. As his mercie therefore, ſo alſo his iuſtice or iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ought with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6686:37"/>moſt hartie affection to be loued, and moſt highly to be extolled and prayſed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Dauid ſayeth: The righteous ſhall reioyce when he ſeeth the vengeance: he ſhall waſhe his handes in the blood of the wicked. For this cauſe the Lorde forbad Samuell 1. Kinges. 16, that he ſhoulde mourne no more for Saul, ſayinge: Howe longe wilt thou mourne for Saul, ſeeing I haue caſt him awaye from reigning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Iſraell? As if he ſayde: Doth my wil ſo diſpleaſe thee, that thou preferreſt mans will before myne? Finally hereupon come thoſe ſayinges of prayſe and ioye through the whole Pſalter, that the Lorde is a Iudge of the widowes, and a Father of the fatherleſſe, that he will auenge the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and iudge the poore: that his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall be confounded, the wicked ſhall be deſtroyed, and many ſuche like. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will with fooliſhe pitie haue compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on that bloody generation, which ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the righteous (yea euen the Sonne of God) &amp; of that exceding great company of the wicked, he ſhal be found to reioyce at their wickednes, and to allow thoſe things that they haue done, being worthy to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6686:38"/>together with them, whoſe ſinnes he would not haue puniſhed: and he ſhal heare that ſaying which is in the ſecond booke of Kinges chap. 19: Thou loueſt thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and hateſt thy frendes. For ſo ſayde Ioab to Dauid, when he too much mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for wicked Abſolon his ſonne. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought here to reioyce at all the godlines of the Sainctes, and the iuſtice of God, who moſt iuſtly puniſheth the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of godlines, that he may deliuer his elect from them. And ſo thou ſeeſt that not ſmall but exceeding good thinges doe manifeſtly appeare in the deade and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: namely, that the iniurie of all the Sainctes is reuenged and puniſhed, and thine alſo if thou be righteous with them. What maruell is it then, if by thy preſent euill he puniſh thine enemie, that is the ſinne of thy body, yea thou oughteſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce becauſe of this moſt excellent benefit of Gods iuſtice, who, thou not deſiring it, ſo ſlayeth and deſtroyeth in thy ſelfe thy worſt enemie, that is, thy ſinne. Whereof if thou haue compaſſion, thou ſhalt be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a frend of ſinne, and an enemie of iuſtice working in thee: which thou muſt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6686:38"/>take heede of, leſt it be ſayd vnto thee alſo: Thou loueſt thine enemies, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy frendes. As therfore thou oughteſt to reioyce on the behalfe of iuſtice being ſeuere againſt thy ſinne, ſo thou oughteſt to reioyce on the behalfe of the ſame alſo, being ſeuere againſt the wicked, which are enemies of men and God. Thus thou ſeeſt that in the greateſt euills are ſeene ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good thinges, and that we may reioyce in the greateſt euills, not becauſe of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills them ſelues, but becauſe of the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne goodnes of iuſtice that deliuereth and auengeth vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The fift chapter of the fift conſideration, which is of the good on the left hand.</head>
               <p>HEre we muſt enter into conſideration of our aduerſaries, who as yet remaine in this life (for in the chapter going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue ſpoken of them that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready damned and in like caſe with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills) theſe we muſt beholde with an other affection, and conſider two ſortes of their good thinges. Firſt that they abound with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6686:39"/>temporall good thinges,
<note place="margin">The wicked moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with temporall good things</note> ſo that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets haue bene almoſt moued euen to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie by their proſperitie, as Dauid Pſal. 72: My feete were almoſt gone, my ſteps had wellneare ſlipt: for I freated at the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, when I ſaw the proſperity of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. And afterwardes: Loe theſe are the wicked, yet proſper they alway, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in riches. Ieremie chap. 12 ſayth: O Lorde thou art more righteous then that I ſhould diſpute with thee, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe let me talke with thee in thinges rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable: Howe happeneth it that the way of the vngodly is ſo proſperous? and that it goeth ſo well with them, which without any ſhame offend and liue in wickednes?</p>
               <p>Why doth he freely poure forth ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good things vpon them,
<note place="margin">God beſtow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of temporall good things vpon the wicked, that he may thereby co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs.</note> and loſe them, but that he may comfort vs, and declare how good he is vnto them which are pure in hart as the ſame 72 Pſalme ſayth. He that is ſo good to the wicked, howe much more good will he be to the godly? albeit he tryeth them with many euills, ſo that not onely in the preſent good thinges, but alſo in them that be hid and as yet to come, they acknowledge him to be good vnto
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6686:39"/>them, and ſaye with Dauid in the ſame Pſalme: As for me, it is good for me to drawe neare to God, to put my truſt in the Lorde. As if he ſayde: Albeit I am ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what troubled, inaſmuch as I ſee them free, notwithſtanding I truſt that God is muche more gracious vnto me then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. And ſo the viſible good thinges of the wicked are a meane to ſtirre vs vp to hope for inuiſible good thinges, and to contemne the euills that we ſuffer, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the commaundement of Chriſt Matth. 6, where he biddeth vs to beholde the foules of the ayre, and the Lillies of the fielde, and ſayth? If God then ſo clothe the graſſe of the fielde, which is to daye, and to morrow is caſt into the ouen, ſhall he not doe much more vnto you, O ye of litle faythe? Wherefore by comparing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the good thinges wherewith the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill abounde, and the euill which we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, our faythe is exerciſed, and wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne comfort in God, which onely is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and true comfort, ſo that all thinges work together for the beſt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saincts.
<note place="margin">The euills of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked turne vnto good to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The other good, which is much more meruelous, is, that their euills are vnto vs
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6686:40"/>good, ſuch a care hath God of vs. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their ſinnes be offenſiue to the weaker ſort, yet to the ſtronge they are an exerciſe of vertue, and an occaſion more ſtrongly to fight, &amp; to obtaine a more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious victorie. For bleſſed is the man that endureth tentation, for when he is tryed he ſhall receiue the crowne of life. Now what is a greater tentation then that multitude of moſt wicked examples? Hereof is the worlde called one of the enemies of the Sainctes of God, for that by the entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and wicked workes thereof it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, prouoketh and allureth from the way of God vnto his owne waye, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Gen. 6: The ſonnes of God ſawe the daughters of men that they were fayre, &amp; they tooke them wiues ſuch as they liked from amonge them all. And Num. 25 it is ſayd that the children of Iſrael committed whoredom with the daughters of Moab, ſo that it is wholſom for vs to be alwayes afflicted with ſome trouble, leſt that being weake, and ſtumbling at the offences of the world, we fal and ſinne. Wherfore Lot is commended of Peter 2. Pet. 2, for that he ſuffered many thinges by the moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6686:40"/>example of the Zodomites, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in righteouſnes hereby. It is needefull therefore that theſe offences come, which may be an occaſion to vs to fight &amp; obtaine the victorie. Notwithſtanding wo vnto the world becauſe of offences. Nowe if in the ſinnes of others God procureth vnto vs ſo great good things, how much more ought we to beleeue with our whole hart that he will worke good vnto vs in our owne euil, although the ſenſe and fleſhe iudge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>No leſſe good doth the worlde bringe vnto vs on the otherſide of his euils,
<note place="margin">The trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and afflictions which the godly ſuffer of the world turne to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie &amp; profit.</note> which is aduerſitie. For whom it can not winne by enticements, neither adioyne to it ſelfe by euill examples, them it endeuoureth by afflictions to expell from it ſelfe, and to trouble them by painefull euills, alwayes either ſeeking deceitfully to entrap them by the example of the wicked, or cruelly raging againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by grieuous torments. For this is that monſter Chimera hauing a head fayre like the head of a virgin, a bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly terrible like the belly of a Lyon, a tayle deadely like the tayle of a Serpent: for the ende as well of the pleaſure as of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6686:41"/>tyrannie of the worlde is poyſon and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deathe. As therefore in the ſinnes of the world God hath made vs to finde good thinges, ſo alſo the perſecutions thereof are not in vaine and fruſtrate, but are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the increaſe of our good things, that euen in that wherein they hurte vs, they may be compelled to profit vs, as B. Auguſtine ſpeaketh of Herode who ſlue the children: He coulde neuer haue profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo much by obedience, as he profited by hatred. And B. Agatha went reioycing to the priſon as vnto a banket, ſaying after this ſorte: Vnleſſe thou make my bodye to be handled throughly of thy tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, my ſoule can not with glorious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie enter into Paradiſe: euen as the grayne if it be not well threſhed &amp; beaten out of the huſke, is not layde vppe in the garner. But why doe we here ſtande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe fewe examples? ſeeing we knowe that the whole Scripture, the writinges and ſayinges of all the Fathers, the works and deedes of all the Sainctes doe agree in this, that they are moſte profitable to the beleeuers, who ſeeme to be vnto them moſte hurtefull, ſo that they be rightly
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6686:41"/>ſuffered and borne: as Peter ſayeth in his firſt Epiſtle chap. 3: And who is it that can harme you, if ye followe that which is good? And Dauid ſayeth Pſal. <hi>88:</hi> The enemie ſhall not oppreſſe him, neyther ſhall the wicked hurte him. Howe ſhall he not hurte him, when he oftentymes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen killeth him? ſurely becauſe by hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting he doth greatly profitte him. So we ſee that we doe on euery ſide dwell in the middes of good thinges, if we be wiſe, and yet alſo in the middes of euills, ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelouſly are all thinges ordered by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the diuine goodnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſixt chapter of the ſixt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, which is of the good on the right hand.</head>
               <p>THis is the Church of the Saincts,
<note place="margin">The good on the right hand.</note> the newe creature of God, our brethren &amp; frends, in whom we ſee nothing but good, nothing but conſolation, howebeit not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fleſhly eies (for according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward appeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they are for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part to be referred to the contrary conſideration
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6686:42"/>of euils) but with ſpiritual eyes. Although euen thoſe their good thinges alſo which are ſeene with fleſhly eies, are not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, but we may perceiue that euen in theſe God doth comfort vs. For Dauid in the <hi>72</hi> Pſalme durſt not diſalow of all that poſſeſſed riches in the world, ſaying: If I ſhould ſay that I woulde iudge after this ſort, lo then I ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy children, that is, if I ſhoulde ſay that all are euill, which are rich, healthful, and had in eſtimation, I ſhoulde then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thy Sainctes, of whome many are ſuch. The Apoſtle moreouer teacheth Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothe to charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not hie minded, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding them to be rich. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scripture declareth that Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob were rich. Daniel with his fellowes were had in honour and reputacion euen in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon: finally many Kinges of Iuda were holy men. Dauid therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering theſe ſayth: If I ſhould ſay that I would iudge ſo, I ſhoulde condemne the generation of thy children. God I ſay giueth to his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of theſe good thinges, to the comfort of them &amp; of others, but theſe are not their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6686:42"/>proper good thinges, yea they are but ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes in reſpect of the true good thinges, which are faith, hope, loue, and other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and giftes, all which are made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon by loue.</p>
               <p>This is the Communion of Sainctes,
<note place="margin">VVhat great ioy &amp; comfort we haue by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Sainctes, which is the good on the right hande.</note> wherin we reioyce. And who doth not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry here euen in great euills, who beleueth, as it is in deede, that the good thinges of all the Saincts are his good thinges, that his euill is theirs alſo, For this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is moſt ſweete and pleaſaunt, whereof the Apoſtle admoniſheth in the Epiſtle, to the Galathians in this ſaying: Beare ye one an others burden, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt. Is it not good for vs to be here, where if one member, as the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>12,</hi> ſuffer, all ſuffer with it: if one member be had in honour, al the members reioyce with it? Therefore when I ſuffer, I ſuffer not now alone, all Chriſtians ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with me, yea Chriſt him ſelfe, as it is ſayd: He that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of myne eye. So others beare my burden, their power is mine, the fayth of the Church helpeth my infirmitie, the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie of others beareth the tentation of my
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6686:43"/>luſt, the faſtings of others are for my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, the prayer of an other is carefull for me, and briefly the members are ſo carefull one for an other, that thoſe which are more honeſt doe couer, keepe, honour them that ſeeme vnhoneſt, as the Apoſtle notably deſcribeth <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>12.</hi> And ſo I may truely reioyce in the good thinges of an other, as if they were mine owne. Be it then that I be foule and filthye, yet they whom I loue, and with whome I reioyce, are fayre &amp; goodly; by which loue I make not onely their good thinges, but euen them ſelues mine. Wherefore my ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſhal be eaſily honoured vnder their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, their abundance ſhal ſupply my want. Who then can deſpeire in ſinne? who doth not reioyce in afflictions, for that he doth not now beare his ſinnes and paynes, or if he beare them, he beareth them not alone, being holpen with ſo many Sainctes that are the ſonnes of God, yea being holpen of Chriſt him ſelfe? So excellent a thing is the Communion of Saincts, &amp; the church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now if there be any that doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that theſe things are thus, he is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6686:43"/>and hath denied Chriſt &amp; the church. For although theſe thinges were not felt, yet are they ſo in deede: but who doth not feele them? For that thou dooſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeire, that thou dooſt not become impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, who is the cauſe? Thyne owne power? no ſurely, but the communion of Saincts. Otherwiſe thou wert not able to beare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a ſmall ſinne, thou couldeſt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the worde of a man agaynſte thy ſelfe: ſo nighe is Chriſt and the Churche. This is that which we ſaye: I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt, the holy Catholike Church, the Communion of Sainctes. Nowe wherein doe the Sainctes communicate?
<note place="margin">As in the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the bread is one though it conſiſt of many graines, &amp; the wine one though preſſed out of many grapes: ſo the Saincts being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of this Supper, though they be many, yet are they me body, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate both in good and euill.</note> euen in good and euill thinges, all things are common amonge them all, as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lordes ſupper doth ſignifie in the breade and wine, we are ſayde of the Apoſtle to be one breade, one body. Nowe who offendeth a part of the body, wherein he offendeth not the whole bodye? what doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> litle toe ſuffer, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body doth not ſuffer? what good is done euen to the feete, wherein the whole body doth not reioyce? But we are one body: whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer an other ſuffereth, I ſuffer and beare
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6686:44"/>it, and whatſoeuer good is done to him, it is done to me. So ſayth Chriſt, that it is done to him, whatſoeuer is done to the leaſt of his. Who taking a peece of the bread of the Lordes Supper, is not ſayd to take bread? who contemning a peece thereof, is not ſayd to contemne bread?</p>
               <p>Wherefore if we be grieued, if we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, if we die, let vs remember and firmely beleue and be aſſured, that not we, or that not we alone, but Chriſt and the Church are grieued, ſuffer and die with vs. Chriſt would not haue vs to be alone in the way of deathe, which euery man dreadeth, but the whole Church accompanying vs, we enter into the way of ſuffering and death, and the Church doth ſuffer more ſtrongly then we our ſelues, ſo that we may truely apply to our ſelues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which Eliſeus ſaid to his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t being afraid: <hi>4.</hi> King <hi>6:</hi> Feare not, for they that be with vs are moe then they that be with them. And Eliſeus pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſayd: Lord I beſeech thee open the eyes of this yong man that he may ſee: and the Lord opened the eyes of the yong man and he looked: and behold the mountayne was full of borſes &amp; charrets of fire rounde
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6686:44"/>about Eliſeus. This onely alſo remayneth vnto vs, that we pray that our eyes may be opened, that we may ſee the Church about vs, that, I ſay, the eyes of our faith may be opened, then ſhall we feare nothing, but ſhall perceiue that to be moſt true which Dauid ſayeth Pſal. <hi>124:</hi> As the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines are about Ieruſalem, ſo is the Lord about his people from henceforth and for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſeuenth chapter of the ſeuenth conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, which is of the good aboue vs.</head>
               <p>I Speake nothing of the eternall and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly good thinges which the bleſſed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy in the manifeſt ſight of God, or at the leaſt I ſpeake of them in faith,
<note place="margin">The good aboue vs, &amp; the moſt ſweete ioy &amp; comfort which the due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof bringeth.</note> and as they may be comprehended of vs. So this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth conſideration is of Ieſus Chriſt, the King of glorye, rayſed from the deade: as the ſeuenth conſideration of euills was of him ſuffering, dead, and buried. Here we may ſee the chiefe ioy of our hart, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and ſure good thinges: here is no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil at all, becauſe Chriſt being raiſed from
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6686:45"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead, dyeth no more: death hath no more dominion ouer him. This is the furnace of loue, and the fire of God in Sion, as Eſai ſayth. For Chriſt is borne vnto vs, and not onely that, but alſo giuen vnto vs. Wherefore his reſurrection is mine, and all thinges that he hath wrought ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. And as the Apoſtle moſt notably glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth Rom. <hi>8:</hi> Howe ſhall he not with him giue vs all thinges? But what hathe he wrought by ryſing agayne? He hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed ſinne, ſet vp righteouſnes, ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp death, &amp; reſtored life: ouercome hell, and purchaſed eternall glorie. Theſe thinges are ineſtimable, ſo that the minde of man dare ſcarce beleeue, that they are giuen vnto him: as Iacob Gen. <hi>45,</hi> when he hearde that his ſonne Ioſeph was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue and gouernour ouer the lande of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, as it were awaking out of a deepe ſleepe, he did not beleeue them that tolde him, vntill they telling vnto him all the wordes of Ioſeph, which he had ſayd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, ſhewed him alſo all the charretts, which Ioſeph had ſent to carie him. So ſurely it is harde to beleeue that ſo great good thinges are in Chriſt beſtowed vpon
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6686:45"/>bs that are vnworthye, vnleſſe in many wordes he declare the ſame vnto vs, and as he made him ſelfe manifeſt to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples by often appearing vnto them, ſo he teach vs ſo to beleeue, as it were by char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets, that is, by vſe and experience. It is a moſt goodly and pleaſaunt charret, that of God he is made vnto vs wiſedome, righteouſnes, ſanctification and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Apoſtle ſayth <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.</hi> For I am a ſinner, but I am caried in his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, which is giuen vnto me: I am vncleane, but his holines is my ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein I am ſweetely caried: I am fooliſh, but his wiſedom carieth me: I am damnable, but his liberty is my redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo that a Chriſtian which beleueth may glory of the merits of Chriſt, and of all his good thinges no otherwiſe then if he him ſelf had done them, ſo properly do they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto him, ſo that he dare now quietly looke for euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgement of God, which notwithſtanding is intolerable. So great a thing is faith, ſo great good things doth it obtaine for vs, ſo glorious ſonnes of God doth it make vs. For we can not be ſonnes, vnleſſe we inherit the good thinges of our
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6686:46"/>father. A Chriſtian therefore may boldly ſay: Death, where is thy victorie? death, where is thy ſtinge, that is, ſinne? for the ſtinge of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law, but thankes be vnto God, which hath giuen vs victorie through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: that is, the lawe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs ſinners, ſinne maketh vs guiltie of death. Who hath ouercome theſe two? Our owne righteouſnes? our owne life? No ſurely, but Ieſus Chriſt rayſed from death, who hath condemned ſinne &amp; death, hath imparted his righteouſnes vnto vs, hath giuen vs his merites, hath layed his hand vpon vs, ſo that we are in good caſe, and doe fulfill the law, and ouercome ſinne and death, for which honour, prayſe and thankes be to God for euer, Amen.</p>
               <p>This therfore is the laſt conſideration, whereby we are now lifted vp not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue our owne euills, but alſo aboue our owne good thinges, and doe now enioy the good thinges of an other, gotten by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers labour, who before were oppreſſed with the euills cauſed by the ſinne of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and increaſed by our owne: We en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy I ſay the righteouſnes of Chriſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6686:46"/>he him ſelfe is righteous, becauſe we cleaue vnto it, by which he pleaſeth God, and maketh interceſſion for vs, &amp; maketh him ſelfe wholy ours, being our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Prieſt and Patron. As vnpoſſible therefore as it is that Chriſt in his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſhould not pleaſe, ſo vnpoſſible is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould not pleaſe by our faith where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we cleaue to his righteouſnes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it commeth to paſſe that a Chriſtian is omnipotent, Lorde of all, poſſeſſing all thinges, doing all thinges,
<note place="margin">A Chriſtian is ſaid to be without ſinne, not in reſpect of the action of ſinne, but inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as ſinne is not imputed to him for Chriſtes ſake.</note> wholy without any ſinne. And although it ſo be that he haue ſinnes, yet can it not be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould hurt him, but they are remitted becauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuincible righteouſnes of Chriſt which ſwalloweth vp all ſinnes, whereunto our faith truſteth, firmely beleuing that Chriſt is ſuch a one vnto vs, as we ſaye. For he that doth not beleue that, heareth in vaine, acknowledgeth not Chriſt, neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth whereunto he profiteth or ſerueth.</p>
               <p>Wherefore euen this one conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if there were no other, may miniſter vnto vs ſo much comfort, if it be well and duely had, that we may not onely not be grieued at our euils, but alſo reioyce in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6686:47"/>ſcarce feeling them by reaſon of the ioy which we haue in Chriſt. Of which ioy our Chriſt our Lorde and God bleſſed for euer make vs partakers, Amen.</p>
               <p>By theſe my cogitations moſt famous Prince,
<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſion.</note> witneſſing after a ſort the duety of my ſmall abilitie, I commende me to your moſt noble grace, being ready to performe greater thinges, if the power of my ſpirit were according to my deſire. For I will alwayes be a dettour both to euery of my neighbours, but eſpecially to your moſt noble Grace, whom our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt by his gracious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes long preſerue among vs, &amp; at the laſt bring to him ſelfe by a bleſſed and happy ende, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Graces moſt humble and obedient ſubiect MARTIN LV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:6686:47"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
